Smallwood Collection
Smallwood Collection
1801-1887
Smallwood, W. M. (William Martin), 1873-1949.
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence and publications of various nineteenth-century naturalists and scientists, primarily Amos Eaton.
2742007
Biographical History
William Martin Smallwood (1873-1949) was an American biologist and a professor at Syracuse University. Smallwood collected books and manuscript material related to the history of science in the United States, much of which he donated to the Syracuse University Library. Most of this collection originated with Smallwood's research for a 1937 article on Amos Eaton.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Smallwood Collection mainly consists of materials directly or indirectly related to the naturalist Amos Eaton. The total collection spans 1801-1887, and the bulk of material comprises incoming letters sent to Eaton from other naturalists and educators between the years of 1817 and 1838. Most of these letters contain scientific enquiries or are related to Eaton's role as a Senior Professor at The Rensselaer School in Troy, New York. Similarly, the manuscript materials and publications all appear to have originally belonged to Eaton and some contain marginal notes. There are also several items indirectly related to Eaton's arrest and imprisonment in 1811 for forgery due to a land dispute. Many of the items are accompanied by typewritten notes and transcriptions by Smallwood.
In addition, the collection includes several items of correspondence unrelated to Eaton, including letters written by Lorenz Oken, Joseph Dalton Hooker, and Thomas Henry Huxley.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is in alphabetical order by correspondent's last name.
Manuscripts and publications are in alphabetical order by author's last name.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science and medicine; New York State; Smallwood, W. M. (William Martin), 1873-1949.; Beck, Lewis C. (Lewis Caleb), 1798-1853.; Beck, Theodric Romeyn, 1791-1855.; Browne, Peter A. (Peter Arrell), 1782-1860.; Cleaveland, Parker, 1780-1858.; Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828.; Clinton, George W. (George William), 1807-1885.; Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842.; Holbrook, Josiah, 1788-1854.; Hall, Frederick, 1780-1843.; Hooker, Joseph Dalton, 1817-1911.; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859.; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895.; Moore, Zephaniah Swift, 1770-1823.; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851.; Oken, Lorenz, 1779-1851.; Phelps, Lincoln, Mrs., 1793-1884.; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840.; Riddell, John Leonard, 1807-1867.; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864.; Steel, John H. (John Honeywood), 1780-1838.; Torrey, John, 1796-1873.; Townsend, Peter S. (Peter Solomon), 1796-1849.; Van Rensselaer, Stephen, 1764-1839.; Woodward, Theodore, 1788-1840.; Brongniart, Adolphe, 1801-1876.; Booth, James Curtis, 1810-1888.; Rensselaer School; Naturalists -- Correspondence.; Troy (N.Y.) -- History.; Correspondence.; Books.; Deeds.; Lecture notes.; Naturalists.; Scientists.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William Martin Smallwood.
Further Eaton letters purchased, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Arnold, Benedict, 1826 (Box 1)
  - Beck, Lewis C., 1829 (Box 1)
  - Beck, T. Romeyn, 1828 (Box 1)
  - Browne, Peter A., 1828 (Box 1)
  - Chilton, 1831 (Box 1)
  - Cleaveland, Parker, 1827 (Box 1)
  - Clinton, DeWitt, 1824 (Box 1)
  - Clinton, George W., 1827 (Box 1)
  - Eaton, Amos, 1828; 1836 (Box 1)
  - Hall, F., 1827 (Box 1)
  - Holbrook, Josiah, 1820 (Box 1)
  - Hooker, Joseph D., Undated; addressed to "Mr. Crookes," also includes portrait engraving of Hooker (Box 1)
  - Humboldt, Alexander von, 1856 (Box 1)
  - Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1887; addressed to "Mr. Crookes," includes portrait engraving of Huxley (Box 1)
  - King, William A., 1825 (Box 1)
  - Locke, John, 1819 (Box 1)
  - Moore, Zephaniah Swift, 1817 (Box 1)
  - Morton, Samuel G., 1829 (Box 1)
  - Oken, Lorenz, 1831; addressed to "Prof. Joh. Ny. Friese," of Innsbruck, Germany (Box 1)
  - Pendleton, Nathaniel, 1803; Smallwood's note: "This letter... is important in showing the sort of contract in which Amos Eaton became involved." (Box 1)
  - Phelps, Almira H. L., 1832; 1838 (Box 1)
  - Rafinesque, C. S., 1826 (Box 1)
  - Riddell, J. L., 1838 (Box 1)
  - Silliman, Benjamin, 1829 (Box 1)
  - Steel, John H., 1821 (Box 1)
  - Torrey, John, 1828 (Box 1)
  - Townsend, P. S., 1818 (Box 1)
  - Van Rensselaer, Stephen, 1825 (Box 1)
  - Woodward, Theodore, 1822; 1823,; 1824 (Box 1)
- Manuscript Material
  - Histoire Des Vegetaux Fossiles by Adolphe Brongniart, 1832; handwritten English translation of Brongniart's work (Box 1)
  - "Animal Physiology" by Amos Eaton, 1817; handwritten notes for a lecture given by Eaton (Box 1)
- Publications
  - Memoir of the Geological Survey of the State of Delaware by James C. Booth, 1841; Eaton's personal copy, given to him by Booth (Box 1)
  - Histoire des Vegetaux Fossiles by Adolphe Brongniart, ca. 1828; Eaton's personal copy with marginal notes (Box 1)
- Legal Documents
  - 1801, Smallwood's note: "While this old deed has no known connection with Eaton... [it] is indicative of the kind of deed which Eaton doubtless drew up during his brief career as a lawyer." (Box 1)
- Duplicates
  - 1801-1887, photocopies of materials in the Smallwood Collection (Box 1)